Ryan A. Green

PHD CANDIDATE · BIOGEOCHEMICAL MODELING · MARINE CARBON DIOXIDE REMOVAL

UC Santa Cruz, 1156 High Street, Santa Cruz, CA 95064

Summary_

My research focuses on utilizing carbon isotopes and biogeochemical modeling to gain insights into past and present carbon cycling dynamics. I investigate these questions using carbon cycle models and regional ocean modeling systems (ROMS). My particular area of interest lies in applying my expertise to marine carbon dioxide removal (mCDR) research, specifically focusing on ocean alkalinity enhancement (OAE).

Education

University of California, Santa Cruz

Santa Cruz, CA

PHD EARTH SCIENCE

2019 - present

• Dissertation: "Advancing Marine Carbon Dioxide Removal through Ocean Alkalinity Enhancement"

University of California, Davis

Davis, CA

BS Environmental Policy

2013 - 2018

- Minor in Oceanography
- · Graduated with honors & departmental citation

Research Experience ___

University of California Santa Cruz - Dept of Earth and Planetary Sciences

Santa Cruz, CA

CO-Advisors: Dr. Mathis P. Hain, Dr. Patrick A. Rafter

2019 - Present

- Developed a regional carbon cycle model to study geologic analogs of Ocean Alkalinity Enhancement (OAE) in the eastern tropical North Pacific
- Simulated a range of OAE deployment scenarios using the California Current System Regional Ocean Modeling System (CCS-ROMS)

University of New South Wales - Climate Change Research Centre

Sydney, NSW

CO-Advisors: Dr. Laurie Menviel, Dr. Katrin J. Meissner

2018-2019

Analyzed seasonal sea-ice cover at the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM). Determined the most likely summer and winter sea-ice
edge at the LGM and constrained the mechanisms controlling sea ice in the different models

University of California, Davis - Dept of Evolution and Ecology

Davis, CA

SUPERVISOR: DR. NICOLE M. KOLLARS

2018

• Assisted in various laboratory techniques, including DNA extraction, polymerase chain reaction, gel electrophoresis, and spectroscopy to investigate the genetic composition of the seagrass species.

University of California, Davis - Dept of Environmental Science and Policy

Davis, CA

SUPERVISOR: DR. LAUREN YAMANE

2017

• Gathered fish life history data from surveys around the Channel Islands. Analyzed and identified key species characteristics, contributing to the development of models that predict species response to Marine Protected Areas (MPAs).

Consulting Experience _____

Oceanid MRV

MCDR Consultant

June 2023 - Present

- Providing scientific expertise on ocean carbon cycling and carbonate chemistry
- Helping develop monitoring, reporting, and verification (MRV) frameworks for different marine carbon dioxide removal (mCDR) pathways

Publicatio	ns	
Published		
	Menviel, L., Meissner, K.J., Crosta, X, Chandan, D., Lohmann, G., Peltier, W. R., Shi, X., and Zhu, J. 2022. nal sea-ice cover over the Southern Ocean at the Last Glacial Maximum. <i>Climate of the Past</i> , 2(1): 100	
IN REVIEW		
	lain, M.H., and Rafter, P.A. 2023. Deglacial Pulse of Neutralized Carbon from the Pacific Seafloor: Co Radiocarbon Budget. <i>Geophysical Research Letter</i> s.	nstraints
In Prep		
	Hain, M.H., Rafter, P.A., and Sun, C. Δ^{14} C Anomalies Explained? Constraints on Neutralized Carbor fastern Tropical North Pacific. <i>Paleoceangraphy and Paleoclimatology</i> .	ı Release
Green, R.A., R	rafter, P.A., and Hain, M.H. Evaluating δ^{13} C as a Tool to Verify Additionality After mCDR.	
Awards, Fe	ellowships, & Grants	
2023	ARCS Fellowship, Achievement Rewards for College Scientists Foundation	\$11,070
2022	Teaching Assistant of the Year, UCSC Earth Science Department	
	Graduate Dean's Research Travel Grant, UCSC Graduate Division	\$500
2021	Teaching Assistant of the Year-Honorable Mention, UCSC Earth Science Department	
2020	Teaching Assistant of the Year-Honorable Mention, UCSC Earth Science Department	
2019	Regents Fellowship, UCSC Earth and Planetary Science Department	\$21,762
	UNSW Summer Vacation Scholarship, UNSW Climate Change Research Centre	\$4,000
2018	University Honors, UC Davis	
	Departmental Citation, UC Davis Environmental Science and Policy Department	
2014-2017	Deans List, UC Davis	
Presentati	ons	
CONTRIBUTE	ED PRESENTATIONS	
	Hain, M.H., Rafter, P.A., Gray, W.R., Rae, J.W.B., and *Sun, C., 2023. Characterizing Geologic Carbon Research for Paging and Alf Canamalian within the Factors Transical North Paging Overlar association.	

- Green, R.A., Hain, M.H., Rafter, P.A., Gray, W.R., Rae, J.W.B., and ⁺Sun, C., 2023. Characterizing Geologic Carbon Release as an Explanation for Deglacial Δ¹⁴C Anomalies within the Eastern Tropical North Pacific. Oral presentation: AGU, Chicago, Illinois.
- **Green, R.A.** 2022. Introduction to Paleoclimatology. Oral presentation: No Jargon Talks, Santa Cruz, California.
- **Green, R.A.**, Hain, M.H., and Rafter, P.A. 2021. Constraints on Geologic Carbon Release at the End of the Last Ice Age from the Planetary Radiocarbon Budget. Oral presentation: AGU, New Orleans, Lousiana.
- **Green, R.A.**, Hain, M.H., and Rafter, P.A. 2021. Constraining Earth's Geologic Influence on the Global Carbon Cycle During the Last Ice Age from the Planetary Radiocarbon Budget. Poster presentation: Goldschmidt, Virtual.
- **Green, R.A.**, Hain, M.H., and Rafter, P.A. 2020. ¹⁴C-Constraints on the Deglacial Release of Geologic Carbon Using Atmospheric Records. Poster presentation: AGU, Virtual.
- **Green, R.A.**, Menviel, L., Meissner, K.J. 2019. Evaluating seasonal sea-ice cover over the Southern Ocean at the Last Glacial Maximum. Oral presentation: PAGES C-SIDE workshop at ICP13, Sydney, Australia.

Teaching Experience		
TEACHING EXPENDENCE —		

Winter 2023	Intro to Environmental Sciences, Teaching Assistant	UCSC
Winter 2022	Intro to Environmental Sciences, Teaching Assistant	UCSC
Winter 2021	Intro to Environmental Sciences, Teaching Assistant	UCSC
Fall 2020	Intro to Computer Programming for Geoscientists, Teaching Assistant	UCSC
Winter 2019	Intro to Environmental Sciences, Teaching Assistant	UCSC
Mentoring		
2023-present	Srishreya Arunsaravanakumar, Research Mentee	UCSC
2022-present	David McCurdy, Research Mentee	UCSC
2021-present	Christopher Sun, Research Mentee	UCSC
2021	Beatrice O'Brien, Research Mentee	UCSC
2021	Caden Kang, Research Mentee	UCSC
2021	Jack Chang, Research Mentee	UCSC
Outreach &	& Professional Development	
SERVICE AND	Outreach	
2014-2017	UC Davis Football Special Olympics, Volunteer	Davis, CA
2014-2017	Shriners Children's Hospital, Volunteer	Davis, CA
2016	Evening of Dreams Special Needs Prom, Volunteer	Davis, CA
LEADERSHIP		
2022-present	International Carbon Ocean Network for Early Career Scientists, Founding Member	Santa Cruz, CA
2018-2019	University of New South Wales, Assistant Football Coach	Sydney, AUS
2013-2017	UC Davis Football, Division-1 Student Athlete	Davis, CA
Profession	al Memberships	

American Geophysical Union Geochemical Society